Every single-cell or Perturb-seq screen
hands you the same puzzle: dozens
of gene programs, each just a ranked list,
none of them
labeled.
Working out what one program actually does
can eat a whole
afternoon on PubMed.
Enrichment gives you a vague heading; a
raw language model gives
you a confident guess that sails right
past the biology.
So we built the Gene Program Interpreter —
a Claude Skill
that reads your programs the way an expert
would, in context,
and shows its work.
Two inputs go in: your weighted program
genes, and any regulators
from a Perturb-seq screen.
First it gives each program an identity —
organism, tissue, cell
type, your conditions, and what these
cells normally do.
The perturbed regulators keep their
direction, and STRING adds a conventional
layer: enrichment, plus an interaction
network wiring each regulator to its
targets.
Now it's a regulatory response in a real
system, not a
nameless list.
Here's the engine.
For every program, we spin up a separate
Claude agent —
all in parallel — to dig through the
literature.
Each one searches PubMed, OpenAlex, and
Crossref with its own tools,
and only ever sees its own brief.
Python runs the fan-out, so a whole screen
researches itself at
once instead of one program at a time.
Then every reference the agents bring back
is checked automatically —
does it resolve, is it retracted, is it a
duplicate.
Anything that doesn't hold up is dropped,
and disagreements and gaps
are kept in plain sight rather than
smoothed over.
Now it all comes together — the verified
papers, the context,
the genes and regulators, the database
evidence — through Anthropic's Batch
API, which writes each program up as clean
functional modules with
a name that fits across the whole set.
It's candid, too.
Click any claim and the real paper opens
in one tap.
And here's a real result.
Program 22 comes back as fructose-driven
lipogenesis — and the giveaway
is its regulator.
Mlxipl, or ChREBP, the master carbohydrate-response
transcription factor, switches the program
on, and the evidence connects it directly
to Khk for fructose,
Pklr for glycolysis, and Fasn for fat
synthesis.
So this isn't a vague "lipid metabolism"
label — it's the
fructose-to-fat pathway, pinned down by
what actually drives it.
And the best part is how little it asks of
you.
A few minutes to set up, and then it runs
itself.
Describe your biology once — a short
context block — and
the same Skill handles the whole pipeline
without touching code.
It works through a whole screen in
parallel while you step
away.
The days you'd spend chasing references
become a hands-off pass —
so your time goes back to the science, not
the searching.